Welcome to our fifth lecture in person
for Stanford deep learning CS230.
Um today's lecture is going to be about
deep reinforcement learning. I actually
switched uh the original plan of talking
about neural network interpretability
and LLM visualization
simply because you you haven't had the
chance to study attention maps, you
know, convolutional neural networks and
so it would have been an overkill to do
that week five. So we're going to talk
about neural network interpretability
and visualization in a later lecture
actually. Um but today our focus will be
on deep reinforcement learning uh which
is probably my favorite lecture of uh
the class. I I feel like I say that
every week but it's okay. I like it. Um
the agenda is pretty packed. We're going
to start with uh deep reinforcement
learning which you can think of as the
marriage between deep learning and
reinforcement learning. Together the
baby is called deep reinforcement
learning. and we're going to see how
reinforcement learning works and how
neural networks can play a part in
building a reinforcement learning um
agent. Um in the second half of the
class we will focus on a very specific
um you know concept called reinforcement
learning from human feedback that you
might have heard of. It's one of the
core concept that
really made the difference between what
you might have remembered as GPT2
and chat GPT. You know, that's the leap.
Uh that's really the the the technique
that had uh that has you know
democratized um access to LLM because of
the performance improvements and the
alignment with humans. So, we're going
to see what what is this concept of R
LHF and how um does it work and why does
it allow us to align a language model to
human preferences.
Ready to go? As always, let's try to
make it interactive.
[snorts and clears throat]
So, the motivation behind deep
reinforcement learning and as usual,
you're going to have all the most
important papers that are covered in the
class listed at the bottom of each
slide. Um reinforcement learning has
grown in popularity. Um one of uh uh the
you know very popular papers called
human level control through deep
reinforcement learning is the work um
from deep mind um has showed us that a
single algorithm/training
method can allow us to train AI that can
play many many Atari games better than
humans. single algorithm over 40 50
games where it exceeds human capability
which is quite impressive when you
thought about the fact that you know
machine learning used to be niche and
you would have to train a really niche
algorithm to perform different task
here's an algorithm that can just learn
sort of every Atari game a little later
you might have heard of Alpho Alph Go is
a is an algorithm that was developed to
beat and exceed human performance
performance in the game of Go. We'll
talk about it a little more. The game of
Go is a very complex game. Some would
argue way more complex than chess from a
decision-m standpoint and from the
possibilities that can happen on the
board. And so, um, it it actually got
solved, um, in 2017 again by the Deep M
Deep Mind team and and David Silver's
lab um, later on. And again another
great paper from deep mind had showed us
that reinforcement learning can also be
used for strategy game that might be a
touch more complex than chess or go that
might actually involve multiple players
playing with each other or against each
other. Some of you might have played
Starcraft for example. That's an example
of a game where um it requires a lot of
long long-term thinking, short-term
thinking. Another one is, you know,
Dota. Some of you might have played Dota
or League of Legend where you have a
team playing against another team. Those
are examples of games that involve
multiple agents playing collaboratively.
And it's pretty hard to develop systems
that can play with each other against
multiple opponents. Um and finally most
recently this is 2022 so alongside the
release of Chad GPT um this paper that
introduces the concept of reinforcement
learning with human feedback applied to
aligning language models with human
preferences and we'll talk about that
later. So all all this to say that
reinforcement learning allowed um us to
exceed human performance in a variety of
tasks. The first one um I want us to
think about is the the game of go. So
let's say that you were asked to solve
the game of go with classic supervised
learning. Okay, everything we've seen
together so far labeled data. How would
you solve the game of go with classic
supervised learning?
What data would you collect? What would
be the label
etc.
Yes.
>> Okay, good point. You look at history of
plenty of games, hopefully from good
players if you want the the algorithm to
work. Um, and you look at X as the input
being the current state of the board and
Y as the next state of the board. And
this would tell you what move was
selected and you learn the move
essentially. And hopefully if you do
that across many many games, you know,
you might you might see the the agent
become more attuned to the game and and
and develop better strategies. So, you
know, really hopefully it's a
professional player. What are the
disadvantages of that or the
shortcomings that you can anticipate?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Great point. You might not
see the entire space of possible states
of the board, which is what you said. So
you might miss out on a lot of different
strategies. So the game of go is
actually a game with two players. One
player that uses the black stones and
one player that uses the white stones.
And iteratively they're going to place
those stones on the grid, a 13 by13 grid
that you can see on screen with the goal
of surrounding their opponent. So you're
constantly trying to surround the stones
of the opponent and the opponent is
trying to surround your stones. And so
you can imagine that for every
intersection on the grid there is
multiple possibilities. Either there's a
black stone or a white stone or nothing.
And on a 13 by13 grid you can imagine
how many possibilities of a board state
there are. It's um impossible to capture
all of that with historical moves from
professional players. It would just
never cover that. The same thing could
be said in chess as well. you you know
that even the professional players can
plan X number of steps in advance but
nobody knows where the game takes you
and in the late stages of the games or
the end games players always find
themselves playing a different game and
that's part of the magic of being good
at chess. [snorts] Um so yeah that's the
problem. What's another problem or
shortcoming beyond the fact that we
can't observe possibly all the states?
Yes.
>> Correct. Correct. You, if I repeat what
you said, well, first, you don't even
know if this was a good move, you know?
So, maybe it was not even a good move
and you're learning something that was
not a good move and you're labeling it
as a good move. And second, um, you're
actually only getting partial
information, meaning you don't have the
information of what's in the person's
mind and what strategy they're trying to
execute. So your store, you're sort of
looking at a single example among a
long-term strategy and you can't expect
the model to guess what's the long-term
strategy because it was just trained on
X and Y and matching the inputs to a
possible output. So you you don't really
have any concept of a strategy at that
point. it looks one off at every
decisions of the model. Okay, those are
really good points. Um the other one is
the ground truth might be illdefined.
What I mean by that is um
even the best humans in the world do not
play their best game every day and even
their best game is not the ground truth.
And that creates an issue because you're
essentially training against a target
that is off by a certain margin. You're
never going to get better than the best
human and the best human is not the best
possible um existing the best possible
strategy at every point. So you could
argue what if we get a panel of experts
that we're monitoring and those are the
best players in the world. Even with a
panel of expert that decides every move,
you're still have an illdefined ground
truth, you know.
So that's a big issue. Too many states
in the game you mentioned and we will
likely not generalize which is what you
said meaning we're looking at one-off
situations. We're not looking at entire
strategies and so when we face a board
state that we've never seen before
because the model was not trained on
strategy it sort of we get stuck. Yeah.
Okay. And this is an example of a
perfect application for reinforcement
learning because reinforcement learning
is all about delayed labels and making
sequences of good decisions. So if you
had to remember in one sentence what's
RL RL is making good sequences of
decisions, sequences of good decisions,
sorry.
and do that automatically.
[snorts] Another way to look at it is
the difference between you know classic
supervised learning and RL is in uh in
classic supervised learning you teach by
example. In reinforcement learning you
teach by experience
which is also a different concept.
You're not just showing cats and
non-cats to a model. You're actually
letting the model experience an
environment until it figures out what
were the best decision it made and
learns from them.
[clears throat] Some examples of
reinforcement learning applications I'm
going to mention them. We we have we
have gaming of course that we already
covered. What are other applications
of AI where we need good sequences of
decisions?
[clears throat]
Yes.
autonomous driving. Yeah, correct. I
mean, in driving, you could argue RL
could work and there's some RL going on,
but what you mean, I think, is you you
have some sort of a dynamic planning
algorithm that allows you to strategize.
If you see a a red light ahead, you
might start slowing down over time, but
maybe it will turn green, so you might
not slow down completely. This is an
example of a strategy that you need, of
course.
>> Yeah.
robotic controlling. That's a great
example also related to autonomous
driving. But imagine you uh want to
teach to a robot to move from point A to
point B. The number of good decisions
that the robot needs to make in terms of
moving each of their joints is
tremendous. Like it's actually super
unlikely that a robot would move from A
to B if it's not trained to make good
sequences of decisions.
What else? Actually,
the biggest one nobody mentioned yet.
>> It's not a great application. I don't
like it, but it happens to be the
biggest one over enforcement learning.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Advertisement. Yeah.
Marketing. You're right. So, yeah, we
talked about robotics. Advertisement is
another example. Um, advertisement
[clears throat]
is a long game. Like companies are
showing you multiple ads before you buy.
And in fact, the reason rein
reinforcement learning is important is
because, you know, they're planning a
strategy that might lead a buyer to
execute a purchase over time and it
requires long-term thinking. So there's
a lot of reinforcement learning applied
to marketing, advertisement, real time
bidding, processes, etc.
Okay, clear on what RL is and how it
differs from classic supervised
learning?
No. Okay. Um, so let's put some
vocabulary around that concept. In
reinforcement learning, you have an
agent and the agent interacts with an
environment.
As the agent interacts with the
environment, the agent will perform
certain actions that we will denote a t
where t is a time step. And the
environment will show you states that
transition from time step t to time step
t + one. So subject to an action at an
environment may transition from a st to
st plus one. You can think of the game
of go. I take the action of putting my
black stone on a certain grid
intersection and the environment has
changed. It moved from the state has
changed. It moved from state time step t
to time step t + one where my stone is
on the grid. After that um state update
happens, there's two things that the
agent observes. the the the agent
observes an observation that we will
note OT and a reward RT.
Okay, so those are the vocabulary words
and of course the goal of the agent will
be to maximize the rewards.
One thing to know about the observation,
we'll talk about it a little more. Um
the observation sometimes is equal to
the state. Can someone guess why we
might need two concepts instead of a
single concept?
Why is it important to have a state and
an observation?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Correct. So in some cases the
environment may not be fully um you know
transparent to the user and so for
example in chess or in go
the observation is actually equal to the
state you see everything on your board
all the information is available to you
if you play League of Legends or
Starcraft
you know the concept of you know I think
in English it's called like a cloud or a
fog I think it's a fog you only see
certain part of the map until you have
explored everything or until your
friends are sort of visiting the other
parts of the map. And so the observation
is actually less information than the
states of the environment.
Okay. And then the last piece of
vocabulary is a transition. When I refer
to a transition, I refer of the process
of getting from state T plus one, which
means we're in state T. The agent takes
an action A. It observes OT and a reward
RT and it transition to the next state
ST plus one. Question.
Uh wait what do you mean? You mean is
there are there examples of environment
where the state is so large that the
entire
[clears throat]
>> Yeah. Possibly for computational
reasons. Yeah. Yeah. You might have
[sighs] games. I mean, look at open
world games. Like truly, you could you
could argue, I don't know, there are
some games where you might press start
and you see the entire environment, but
who cares of what's happening 20,000
kilometers west of you if you're in a
certain location. That might not
influence your strategy. So you might
actually put some sort of a you know
trust circle or like some sort of a
circle in which you observe which you
think has 99% of the information you
need possibly for computational reasons.
That's a good point.
Okay, let's get to a practical example
of a reinforcement learning algorithm
and develop it together.
This example is called recycling is good
because recycling is good but also
because it's a simple example
illustrative of reinforcement learning.
So let's say we have a a small
environment with uh five states. There
is a starting state marked in brown
which is state two. It's our it's our
initial state. And then on the right
side, sorry, on the left side, you have
state one, which is a garbage. And it's
great to get to the garbage because
you're going to be able to recite to to
put in the garbage the, you know, the
stuff that you have in your hands. You
know, you're trying to throw away some
garbage and the garbage can happens to
be there and so we would expect there to
be a reward. On the other side, if you
actually go to the right, you might pass
by state three, which is empty. You
might pass by stage four where there is
a chocolate uh packaging that is left on
the ground that you can pick up and it's
good to pick it up. And then on stage
five, state five, you have the recycle
bean which is more valuable than the
garbage can because you can recycle and
you should get better rewards for that.
So that's our game. In this game, we
define a reward that is associated with
the type of behaviors that we want the
agents to learn. Um, and the reward is
as followed. That's just one example.
Plus two for throwing your garbage in
the normal can, plus one for picking up
the chocolate packaging, and plus 10 if
you manage to make it to the recycle
bin.
Is it clear?
Now, the goal will be, and that's the
case in reinforcement learning often
time to maximize the return.
We'll define formally the return but
think about it as maximize the amount of
rewards that you get as you go through
this journey and you make your
decisions. In this specific game, we
have five states and there's three types
of state. In brown is the initial
states. We have normal states and we
have in blue terminal states. When you
get to a terminal states in
reinforcement learning, it will
typically end the game. it will end one
episode of the game. You move to another
episode. You'll get back to the starting
state or initial state and you'll redo
another episode.
The possible actions for our agent here
are going to be fairly simple. Left and
right.
And we're going to add an additional
rule that is important, which is that
the garbage collector comes in 3 minutes
and it takes a minute to get from one
state to the other. Why is that an
important rule to add to the game?
Can you guess?
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Otherwise, you just go back and
forth between uh stage three and stage
four. You just collect a bunch of
chocolate packaging and you never make
it to the bin. And so, it's not what we
want. Yeah.
[snorts] Okay. So, how do we define the
long-term return? The long-term return
is going to be defined as capital R,
which is the sum of rewards with a
discount.
Discount is a very important concept in
reinforcement learning. It's also a very
natural concept to think about. Can you
think of what what the discount would
represent in for humans? Do you have an
example of what it could be? Yeah.
>> Huh? money.
>> Yeah. The value of money and time.
Exactly. Or the energy that a robot
might have, things like that. Yeah. You
you would rather get, you know, a dollar
now than a dollar in 10 years knowing
that there's some inflation, for
example. That's the example of a
discount. In reinforcement learning is
the same. You know, let's say you have a
strategy that takes so much time. You
need to discount it because your robot
might lose energy as you're going
through it. For example, these counts
can vary, you know, but they stay
between zero and one.
Um, so what is the best strategy to
follow if gamma the discount is equal to
one meaning you know time doesn't matter
here if it's longer or shorter just want
to maximize the return.
Best strategy to follow.
Let's give it a try.
Someone who hasn't spoken yet.
>> Yes.
>> Bounce around. But remember the rule of
uh 3 minutes.
You can't bounce around because you you
will not get to the terminal state
before the time allotted is done. But
that would be a good idea if this rule
was not true.
What else could you do?
The idea? It's an easy one. No, it's not
too hard.
best strategy for gamma equals 1 and
give me also the maximum reward you
would get.
People are are sleepy today. Yeah.
>> Recycle.
>> Go to the recycle. So, right, right,
right.
>> Yeah, that's right. Thank you.
Right, right, right. And then what's
your Sorry. What's your um what's your
total reward?
Yeah, that's right. 11. So that's where
we get terminal state and we grab our
reward of 11. Very good. Now assuming
0.9 for gamma. We're going to complexify
things a little bit. I'm going to walk
you through a very simple algorithm that
you know allows us to sort of determine
the best strategy and we will put our
numbers in a matrix. So for instance um
we'll define a Q table and Q stands you
know is a it's a it's a value function
um where the the the name Q-learning
Q star you might have heard um all of
these things come from Q-learning and so
let's say we have a Q table which has uh
the size of number of states times
number of actions so five rows two
columns in our
Every entry of the Q table is
essentially representing how good it is
to take action
A in state B.
Do you agree that if we had a table with
these numbers essentially we solve the
problem meaning at any point the agent
can just look in the table I am in state
three let's look at column one that
would tell me the value of action one
and let's do that column two it would
tell me the value of action two so I
have everything I need to make my
decisions
so that table is really the the thing
you want to find in this exercise now
the way we will find the table is sort
of using a backtracking algorithm where
we might actually
codify the environment as a tree and
traverse the tree. So here's what it
looks like. I start in S2 and I have two
options ahead of me. I can go to the
left where I will get a reward of two.
It's an immediate reward. The immediate
reward is not discounted. It's an
immediate reward. Remember the the
formula for R. The immediate reward R0
is not discounted. That would take me to
S1.
It's a terminal state, so there's
nothing to do after.
[snorts]
Second option, I go to the right and I
get a reward of zero. That's my
immediate reward. And I end up in state
three. State three is not a terminal
state. So I can go and do the same
exercise from state three. In state
three, I have two options. I can go to
the left where I would see a reward of
zero and I will end up in S2 or I will
go to the right and I will get an
immediate reward of plus one. It's an
immediate reward. We're not discounting
it. I will end up in S4 and from S4
again I have two options. Back to the
left to S3 with zero reward or to the
right with the amazing reward of plus 10
and the terminal state of S5. So that's
my map of immediate rewards. That's not
my discounted return. So what we're
going to do now is we're going to
backtrack up the tree in order to
compute the discounted returns.
Actually, if I'm in S3 right here,
I see that I can get an immediate reward
in S4 of one. And I want to compute my
maximum return that I can get from when
I'm in S3. My maximum return is that in
S4 I could get a plus 10, right? But I
need to discount that. My discount is
0.9. So I multiply 10 by 0.9. What it
tells me is that from S4 I can expect
nine plus one, which I get as an
immediate reward from moving from S3 to
S4, I can update this number to 10.
Meaning from S3 the best you can hope
for is a discounted return of 10 which
is 1 plus 0.9* 10.
Everyone follows.
Now let's do the same exercise one step
before in S2. uh you know um in S2 um I
have um an immediate reward of zero for
going to S3 or an immediate reward of
two for going to S1. Um S1 is not going
to be worth it. We already know that
because when I'm in S3 I can actually
expect 10 which I have to discount. 0.9
* 10 gives me 9 plus 0 immediate reward
from S2 to S3. That tells me that the
discounted return from state two which
is our initial state is nine.
Good follow just a simple backtracking.
Now I can copy back this. So S3, I know
that when I'm in S3, um uh you know, I
can expect zero immediate reward to um
uh to sorry, if I if I'm if I'm in S2, I
can expect uh zero immediate reward plus
a discount times the plus 9 that I could
expect in S3. And so that gives me
values that should cover everything that
we have in this Q table. So I I do that
backtracking. I copy paste all of that
into my Q table all the way up here. And
this is what I get.
We essentially finish the game at this
point. We um can look uh at a certain
row. So let's say I'm in state number
three. I look on the third row of that Q
table and I see that I have two options.
If I go back to S2,
ultimately my discounted return will be
8.1,
right? If I actually go to S4 on the
right, I will get 10 because I will get
1 + 0.9 * 10, which is 10.
So this is a toy example, but it tells
you that if you were able to backtrack
through the entire environment, you will
be able to build a massive Q table and
you will be able to give it to your
agent to make its decisions.
[snorts]
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry, can you repeat?
>> Yeah, here I'm simplifying. I'm not
considering the time uh remaining. But
in practice um you if if I remove the
time component so I remove the fact that
there's a three minute deadline before
the garbage collector comes then uh this
would uh be slightly more difficult
because you would have to do a time
series essentially of adding the
discount times the reward that you
collect. Yeah, but I'm simplifying here
and that's why I use the three-minut
rule.
Any [snorts] question on the Q table?
Super. Okay. So, uh this was the Q table
and in fact [clears throat] we can put
together our strategy for gamma equals
0.9.
The best strategy is still the same. You
go to the right and you can expect a
return of 9.
Now, one of the most important concepts
in reinforcement learning is this
equation on the board called the Bellman
optimality equation.
Often time you'll see it noted as Q star
of state S and action A
equals R + gamma time the max of that
same function applied to S prime A
prime.
Let me explain this equation for you
because it's super important. This
equation is called the optimality
equation because your optimal Q table
will follow this equation. If you have
finished the game, this equation can be
applied to any state action pair and it
will still be true.
The intuition behind why the Bellman
equation is the optimality equation is
that um if you're in a if you have the
perfect Q function Q table um and you're
in a certain state and you perform a
certain action A you will observe a
reward and this reward will uh you know
you you have taken an action so you
would be in a new state and from that
new state you can repeat what you just
did right and because uh you've done the
backtracking and stuff like that, you
will uh get this equation to be true
because it's the reward plus discount
times the best next action that you
could be taking.
Does that make sense? Any question on
that?
That's exactly the backtracking that we
did by the way. immediate reward plus
discount times the best possible action
that you can take in the next state s
prime.
[snorts]
The last concept I cover in terms of
vocabulary is the policy. The policy is
the function that given your state is
going to tell you what to do. And in
Q-learning the way this policy is
defined is argmax of Qstar um across the
action. So essentially what it says is
like look in the table and look at a
certain state s you want the policy
which is what you should do. It's the
function that tells you our best
strategy. You just look at the two
possible actions which one has the
highest Q value and select that action.
That's it.
This is a very simple example but it
it's the core of um Q-learning that you
know later on you will use policies
widely. There's a lot of reinforcement
learning algorithms but this concept of
understanding the policies the function
telling us our best strategy in
Q-learning it's the argmax of the best Q
value in the given state. It tells you
which action to take that's the core
thing you need to understand.
>> [snorts]
>> So remember this belman equation because
we're going to reuse it
in a bit. The main issue um with this
approach um of a Q table is that state
and action spaces can be super large and
having a matrix that you discover
through backtracking
um and where every time you want to do
an action you have to look up the given
state the possible action it becomes
impossible. Like imagine you using this
algorithm for the game of go where
there's so many states, there's so many
possible actions, you can put your stone
anywhere on the board. You can imagine
how big this matrix becomes and how
impossible it is to use. So that's our
problem and that's the moment where deep
learning comes into play.
So let's look at it. uh
the the the oh actually before I go
there I'm just going to cover some
vocabulary. We said the environment, the
agent, the state, the action, the
reward, the total return and the
discount factor. We learned all of that.
We saw that the Q table is the matrix of
entries representing how good is it to
take action A in state S. And the policy
is the function that tells us what's the
best strategy to adopt. And the bellman
equation is satisfied by the optimal Q
table.
So let's get to deep Q-learning which is
what I was about to say is we are going
to frame the problem slightly
differently. So instead of using a Q
table, we're going to use the fact that
neural networks are universal function
approximators and we're going to define
a Q function that's essentially a neural
network. So that the function can take a
state S and an action A and tell you how
good that action is in state S. So
instead of a lookup in a matrix, you
just run a forward pass in a neural
network and it gives you the answer.
That feels like a better solution for
games where there's a lot of states and
a lot of actions.
So here is a same problem statement. In
the past we looked for a Q table and
this time we will look for a neural
network. One of the things we're going
to do is to define the output layer to
have two outputs. So given a certain
state as input think about it as a one
hot vector encoding the state. So this
one is the example of state two 0 1 0 0
0. If you pass state two in this Q
function with multiple layers, it will
give you two outputs. One output that
corresponds to Q of S
action right and the other one Q of S
action left because it's the two
actions.
If we had more actions to take, we would
just increase the output layer and we
might have many more neurons in the
output layer.
So the big question is how the hell are
we going to train that network? Because
we're not in classic supervised
learning. We don't have labels.
So this one is a hard question but u
what do you what would you do given we
we don't have traditional x and y pairs
how are you going to train this neural
network
because remember at the beginning this
neural network will give you garbage it
will take a state s and it might tell
you go to the left or to the right but
it's completely random so how are you
going to tune it to the level where it
makes really Good decisions.
Yes.
>> Assume based on some prior knowledge.
Tell me more. What?
>> So what are the things we know about
this problem right now? What are the the
the rules of the game that we could use
in order to
I'm I'm seeing what you say. You say we
could estimate what good looks like but
based on what?
>> Okay. So reward structure you're saying
that's one thing we have in every game.
We have a reward structure for every
state that definitely should be used in
order to estimate the good what a good
decision looks like. Yeah. The problem
is not in every state you will see a
reward. And if you look at many games of
like go you might not see a reward until
50 moves.
>> So what do you do in this case?
>> Yes. Can we run through a bunch of
actions and space and see what the
output is and get more data?
>> Yeah. So you could you're actually um
bringing up a sort of a tree search,
right? You go down the tree, you do
every possible action and then you
backtrack.
>> Not every possible action.
>> So which actions?
>> Trying to spread it out of the
>> Okay, that's that's we're getting there.
So first possibility is we just go down
the tree in the game of go. You could
put your stone everywhere. So the tree
already start by a 13 by3 options and
then it's exponentially grows
impossible. It's intractable. But what
you said is what if there are certain
actions that are more likely than
others? Do we need actually to explore
the entire tree? What's this like? What
are you using when you're saying that?
How do you determine what action might
be better than another one?
>> Expected return. And we're getting
close. Yeah. But you know, how do you
know the expected return without going
through the tree once? At least
>> you can estimate both.
>> Okay. You can estimate it using what?
>> Yeah, maybe. Yeah. What? What? So that's
exactly what we're going to do actually.
But we're going to use the the Bellman
equation because there are two things we
know about this problem. We know the
reward structure which you brought up
and we also know that the perfect Q
function will follow the Bellman
equation that we know as well. At the
end the Bellman equation should be
respected meaning for every state if you
want to know the Q value of that state
given an action. The way you will get
that is you will look at the immediate
reward plus the discount times the best
Q value from the next state across all
actions. that equation will be
respected. So those are the only
information we have and we're going to
use them drastically to define our
labels and sort of mimic a classic
supervised learning approach. So here's
what we have. We have our neural
network. We have Q S to the left and QS
to the right that represent how good it
is to go to the left in that state
versus the right. And then I've pasted
the Bman equation on top right of the
screen. We're going to define a loss
function. So let's say for the sake of
simplicity because those are scalar
values that will use you know L2 loss
quadratic loss that compares a certain
label Y to um a certain Q value of a
state and a certain action. So what we
would like is to minimize this loss
function meaning Y and the Q value for a
given action in a given state is as
close as possible to each other. and
we're going to leverage the reward and
the Bman equation. So let's do um two
things. Right now we don't have a Y. So
in supervised learning you will have a
picture of a cat. There's a cat. The Y
is one or zero. Here we don't have a Y.
So we have to come up with an estimate
of a good Y at least better than random.
So let's say at this point in time when
I send a state S in the network, it
turns out that Q of going to the left is
higher than Q of going to the right.
Which means that today at that moment
the Q function tells me it's better to
go to the left than to go to the right.
That is random at the beginning. It's
completely random. Right? So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to use as my
target value Y the immediate reward that
I observe on the left
plus gamma times the best Q value that I
can get. So the best action that I could
take in the next step based on my
current Q value.
That's very important. So remember this
target is off. It's not a perfect
target, but it's better than nothing.
Meaning, not only it tells us, hey,
there is a good reward to the left. We
should consider that in saying that that
might be a good move because we're
seeing an immediate reward. But on top
of that, we also know that at the end of
training, the Q value should follow the
Bellman equation. So why don't we set
the target as the Bellman equation? So
we add the discounted maximum future
reward when you are in the next state.
So you were in state S. You go to the
left now you're in state S next left and
you look again at your Q values and you
select the best one. Then you add that
number here. [gasps] So there is
actually two forward path in that
process.
Right?
There's one forward path where you send
the state S in Q and you look at the two
options left or right and you're like
okay I'm going to the left and then
you're like I'm going to compare that
value to a target Y but to get that
target Y I need to do another forward
path. So I take my action left I perform
it I get an S prime state s next and I
send that S next into the Q network. I
look at the two options I have. I pick
the best one and I add it here with a
discount.
So fundamentally what's happening is is
the following is we have a Q network
that's random at [clears throat] the
beginning. It has never observed the
rewards. We just know that at some point
it will get to the Q um it will get to a
perfect you know policy. It will get to
a perfect Q function. But the best we
can do right now is to say as a guide to
for our agent, we will look at the
immediate reward and we will look at the
Bellman equation which should tell us a
better estimate than where we are right
now and we will try to catch up to that
estimate and then we do that again and
again. So remember every time your Q
gets better it gets better for the next
state as well. So you know the Bellman
equation tells you estimate it with the
second forward path and you just keep
getting better and better as you're
observing more rewards.
[clears throat and snorts]
left
and
>> uh how would it so describe the loop you
[clears throat]
>> imag
>> for going to a right you again need the
target
>> yeah you would stop at that point so
what you yeah this is a good question I
I'll show you how we fix certain things
but you do only one step meaning
you have your Q value at this point and
it tells you go to the left and you just
want to target Y. So what you do is you
put left and you look at your next
state. You forward propagate your next
state. You look at the two options. You
pick the best. You don't go further. You
just use that one step. You look one
step ahead essentially. You don't look
multiple steps ahead. You could, but it
would be more computationally heavy to
do one more step again and so on.
So yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It seems like you're learning the
function locally like
most
people know like how fast that
>> it will typically be a function of the
environment the state space um how long
it will take to converge but you're
perfectly right that um as the Q
function gets better, the estimate Y
also gets better. So the two things get
better together, right? Because the Y is
based on the Q function. And if the
state space is massive, you might have a
very difficult time training this model.
There's better approaches that we'll see
later.
Yeah, correct. There was a question
there.
>> Yeah. So here I'm just saying let's say
when you send state S in Q the left
happens to be higher than right. But the
same happens on the other side. Let's
say let's say the left is worse than
right. Then what you will do is you will
define your target Y as the reward that
you observe on the right plus from the
next state of having gone to the right
what's the best action and what's the Q
value for that pair and then it will
give you the target for that scenario.
So one complication with this training
is that when you want to differentiate
L. So you want to perform a back
propagation. You want to take the
derivative of L with respect of the
parameters of the network. You want Y to
be a fixed thing, right? Because in
supervised learning Y is not
differentiable. It's just a fixed number
zero or one or a certain number. So here
we're going to simplify and we're going
to say this term that is dependent on
the Q network. So technically this term
has parameters. So if you actually
differentiate it, it will give you a
value. We'll just hold it um fixed. So
we say we do use our Q network to
perform an estimate of our Y but we will
not differentiate it. We will say it's
not it's fixed. Yeah.
>> Can you explain why we discount this?
>> Yeah.
>> Because you know going back to the
reason we discount is like the value of
time. It's like you probably want to say
if you can win the game in 10 moves, win
it in 10 moves rather than 100 moves. Um
or if you can get $1 today, get $1 today
rather than in 10 years. All of that is
why we have a discount here. And the
discount is a is a hyperparameter that
you would define as well. That would
influence the strategy of your agent.
>> Once more pass.
>> We're going to see it after. Actually,
I'm going to do a concrete example
because it's a little complicated. Yeah.
Yeah.
>> Q.
>> No, no, that that was it's a good point.
It's not that. It's just Q of it's it's
a 2 by two. It's a one by two. So you
have left and right. I was just going
down the first case. So I put the state
left. Yeah. Yep.
>> What if the rewards are not fixed? I
mean, in most games we're going to see
right now, the rewards are going to be
fixed by the designer of the game, the
human that's designing the game. Um, in
practice, you could have a separate
function that um actually comes up with
the reward. We're going to see an
example later in the lecture where the
reward might be different in different
scenarios and there's a function or
sometimes called a critic that
determines what's the reward in a
certain state.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, this is yeah one last question and
then we move because we we're going to
see a concrete example is going to be
clear.
>> Um so when we like hold it fix for
laptop is that what differentiates this
from iterating through all of the like
possible
>> Yeah. Yeah. So instead of doing the
backtracking down the tree and going
over everything, we're saying we're
going to limit oursel to just picking
the best action based on our current
understanding of the network.
You see, like my network is kind of
intelligent, not great. We're in the
middle of training. It says that I
should go to the left and then if I look
at the next state when I'm in the left,
it says I should go to the right. I will
trust it because it's the best I have,
best estimate I have, but I will
discount that. And then if you keep
repeating that, it turns out that not
only your estimate gets better, but your
model gets trained and then ultimately
both together get to an optimality
equation.
So it's a it's a funky concept, right?
But you get it.
We're going to see examples. Um, okay.
So uh then once you have been able to
use the Belman equation to estimate your
targets, you perform classic back
propagation and you update the
parameters of the network and you repeat
that process.
Okay.
[snorts]
Uh here is concretely if you were to
code it in pseudo code, here is what it
would look like to train a NRL agent
using Q-learning. We start by
initializing our Q network parameters.
So initialization, it's random at first.
Then we will loop over episode. As a
reminder, episodes are one full game
from start to terminal state. Um within
an episode, we're going to start from
the initial state s and we're going to
loop over time steps until we reach a
terminal state. So within one time step,
here's what we will do. We forward
propagate the state s in the Q network.
We will execute the action A that has
the maximum Q value.
We will observe a reward and we will
also observe a next state S prime. We
will use that S prime to compute our
target Y by forward propagating S prime
in the Q network and then computing our
loss function. And based on that we will
use gradient descent to update the
parameters of the network
should be simpler looked at like that
right
okay so this is the vanilla Q-learning
so to summarize again the one the main
difference is that we don't have a
target and we use our own network to
estimate the target and the rewards are
what's going to help us get better over
By the way, it's okay if you don't
understand everything. This is an entire
class at Stanford. Um, you know, an
entire quarter of studying that type of
stuff. So, we're trying to get the
basics within an hour and a half, two
hours.
Okay, let's go a little further now
together um
and apply that to an actual game. So,
here's the game. It's called Breakout.
We want to destroy all the bricks. Who
has played Breakout in the past? Buddy,
a few. Okay, good. So, you have a a
paddle that you control and you're
trying to destroy the bricks. If the
ball gets past your paddle, you lost.
And if the bricks are all destroyed, you
won. That's it.
Let's do it together.
What um what is the input of our Q
network?
What would you use as input
to remember? Yeah. [clears throat]
Yes.
[snorts]
>> Entire screen. Okay. Let's do that. So I
take I define that as the state S which
is the input to my Q network. Uh what's
the output of the Q network?
>> Yes.
>> Do we have to do that on screen?
>> Good question. We'll get there. I'm I'm
gonna ask you, but do we have to look at
the full screen? Answer is no, but we'll
see why. What's the output?
>> Yeah.
>> Game score.
>> The game score. Uh, no. But we're going
to talk about the game score in the
back.
>> Yeah. Let's let's talk about the output
first and then we'll talk about the
stuff we can get rid of on the inputs.
But what's the output? Yeah,
>> it's the
the actions.
>> Yeah, the actions. So, yeah, it will be
the Q values
associated with the actions in state S.
Remember, it's a Q function. So, the
output is we need one value for left,
one value for right, and one value for
idle. [snorts] You could make this game
more complicated and say we have eight
actions. We have a little bit to the
left, a lot to the left, a lot more to
the left. You know, if you had multiple
buttons, but let's simplify and say
three actions. Either you don't move,
you move to the left or you move to the
right. So these are the outputs. So now
let's get to the question of the screen.
Do we need the entire screen?
>> So you were saying something earlier?
[snorts]
>> Okay. So you say you need the tray and
the bricks. I would argue uh you need
more because there's the walls. And I
guess that you could if you're an expert
player, you could know where the walls
are, but generally you need a little
more than that. What what what would be
obviously things we can get rid of? And
why would we do that?
>> The background.
>> Okay. The score, the score at the top.
>> Um, who would remove the score at the
top?
About half.
Why would you not remove it?
>> Why would you remove it?
>> Okay, you want to always win. So the
score doesn't matter. It's true. We
would remove the score. So you you could
actually crop the top. You could also
crop the bottom. I mean, if it passed
the paddle, you don't care about the few
pixels at the bottom. You could get rid
of them. Um this is not always true.
There are games where the score matters
and in fact you know I like football
soccer the the in soccer if you're one
zero up you can park the bus. So your
strategy is dependent of the score that
you have like you wouldn't park the bus
if you're losing one zero. Parking the
bus meaning you ask every player to come
back and defend. If you're losing you
would actually do the opposite. You will
go all out attack. So in certain games
you want the scores, in others you don't
want. And so it's part of the designer,
the the the AI engineer that's working
on that to determine what information we
need and what we don't need. What else
could we do to reduce the dimensionality
of the problem and make our computation
faster?
>> Yeah, remove the RGB channels. So do
grayscale essentially. That's true. Here
you actually don't need the colors. It's
[clears throat] just nice as a user for
user experience purposes. you don't
need. I don't think there's different
points based on the bricks that you
destroy. It's all the same. Um there
actually, funny enough, this algorithm
was used by um Deepine to play a lot of
Atari games and they did a single
pre-processing where they removed the
channels because they said it doesn't
matter. Turns out in one of the games, I
think it was CQS, I forgot which one,
the fish disappeared when you did that.
And so that game didn't work. the the
agent couldn't crack it uh because they
thought that the same pre-processing
could apply to every game, but actually
they had to make a slight tweak.
also
>> correct
>> you. So just to recap, you could do it
even better by using a a low dimensional
representation of this game that
describes the game. It's true, but
because we want to use a single
algorithm for 50 plus Atari games, we'll
say the human sees the screen, we'll
just give the screen and it will
probably scale better essentially. But
you're perfectly right if you were
working on only that game. Okay, so
let's do that. We'll we'll do
pre-processing. There's one last thing
that nobody mentioned which is history
because in fact if you get only one
screen you don't know where the ball is
going. So actually you can't solve the
game and the way you fix that is by
giving a history of multiple screens for
example four screens so that you see the
direction that the ball is going in. So
our pre-processing function is you know
called f ofs let's say and f ofs is a
mix of um you know you might do convert
to grayscale reduce the dimension the
height and width and also add the
history of four frames and that should
be enough.
Turns [clears throat] out in most games
you will need a history a little bit of
history to know where the ball is going
or
>> in this example can just encode the uh
like velocity vector of the ball. Yeah,
you could you could replace exactly you
could replace
um the history so multiple screen by
just adding the gradient or the velocity
of where the ball is going. That's true.
But would it scale to every game? You
know, turns out this because we know
humans look at the Atari machine and
they look at pixels. This would be more
likely to scale to every game.
Like think about a game where actually
sequest is a good game or space invaders
where you have multiple enemies coming
at you then you would need to change
your pre-processing to take into account
the velocity of all these enemies. So it
wouldn't work the same way. While if you
actually give the pixels you actually
from the pixels get the velocity of all
your enemies and the directions they're
going.
Okay. So this is our pre-processing. I'm
going to refer to it as fs. And um our
deep Q network architecture because
we're working with pixels is going to be
um a convolutional network. Don't worry
if you haven't learned it yet in the
class, but it's a bunch of con and relu
activations. Um and then we end with a
fully connected layer that gives us the
three Q values for uh the different
actions.
So nothing special here. Now, uh, we're
going to go back to our vanilla
training. So, this one that we saw
together earlier, and we're going to
look at tips to train reinforcement
learning algorithms. Those tips are not
specific to Q-learning. Some of them are
applied to a lot more than Q-learning,
and they're very important to know. Um,
and they're part of the reason
reinforcement learning has worked better
in the last few years. Um, so one of the
things that's pretty simple that we
forgot to do um is the pre-processing
that we just did. So anywhere I had an
S, I'm going to instead run S through
the pre-processing step, I'm going to
use PH of S. So I initialize instead of
S with P of S. I start from the initial
state of S and then I for propagate f of
I um I get the Q of that pre-processed
state in action A and etc. etc. And then
when I get my next state, so let's say I
look at my current pre-processed state,
I forward propagate it once. I see the
three Q values, in our case, the two Q
values. One of them was better than the
other action, right? Then I get my next
state S prime. I want to pre-process
that state as well. Yeah, so that's
pretty straightforward. You just replace
all of that.
>> [snorts]
>> The second thing we forgot to do is to
keep track of the terminal state. In our
pseudo code, there is no concept of
terminal state. It's pretty easy to add.
You would probably just do an if else
statement. You would create a boolean to
detect terminal state. So let's say your
boolean is terminal equals false. And
then as you loop over the time step of a
single episode, every time you're going
to check, is the state that I'm going in
based on the action I'm taking a
terminal state? If it's a terminal
state, then get out of the loop. You
know, there's nothing else after. The
one thing that you need to be careful of
is if it's a terminal state, then your
target is not the Bellman equation. It's
just the the immediate reward. Remember,
you get to the terminal state, you get a
reward of 10. There's no Bellman
equation to apply. It's just 10. It's
immediate reward. There's no discount,
etc.
Okay, so these are fairly easy changes.
Now, we're going to look at a new method
that will enable more data efficiency.
It's called experience replay. One of
the a couple of issues with the way
we've been training so far is one the
correlation of successive screens. It's
like imagine in the Atari game you have
the ball that's in the top left corner
and it's traveling to the bottom right
of the screen. You have like many many
time step that are essentially the same.
It's all the ball traveling in the same
in the same place. So you're actually
training repetitively on something that
is not that meaningful. You don't need
to just train on a batch. The equivalent
in supervised learning is let's say
you're trying to differentiate cats and
dogs and you train on a mini batch of
cats, then you train on a mini batch of
dogs, then you train on a mini batch of
cats, and it will never converge. It
will just index too much on cats and
then index too much on dogs. So you want
to add some sort of a
experience replay concept that we'll see
in order to create more mixes in the
data and get more diversity. The other
thing that is important is in our
current training process, we are not
reusing our data. Like you experience
something, you immediately train on it.
You never see it again unless you
reexperience the same thing sometimes in
the future, which might or might not
happen. Experience replay is going to
help us to keep experiences in memory
and maybe retrain on them on a regular
basis so that one experience might be
useful multiple times
which intuitively makes sense. Like
maybe you do an experience, you get an
amazing reward and you don't want to
forget it. You want to retrain the model
on it on a regular basis. It's more data
efficiency. So here's what it looks
like. Um, the current way we were
training was we're in a state I'm just
going to say state instead of
pre-processed state, but it's
pre-processed. We're in a state S. We
perform action A, we get a reward R, and
we get into the next state. From that
next state, we perform another action A
prime, we get a reward RP prime, and we
get into S second and so on, you know,
and so on. And each of these would be
called one experience. It's one
iteration of gradient descent. It's one
experience. So right now we're training
on these experiences. So the training
looks like I train on E1, I update my
parameters. Then I train on E2, I update
my parameters. Then I train on E3,
update my parameters. Those are highly
correlated because they're part of the
same episode. And as I was saying with
the ball traveling in one direction,
that might actually not be that helpful
to train on all of these, you know. So
instead what we'll do is we'll use
experience replay where we will collect
our first experience but instead of
training on it we will put it in a
memory called the replay memory D. We'll
put it in there and then at every step
we will sample from that memory to
decide what to train on. So of course at
the beginning if we just have one uh
experience in the memory we will train
on that experience. But over time you
will see that we get more diversity and
reuse out of our experiences. So for
example, let's say I experience E2, I
put it in the memory and then instead of
training on E2, I'm going to randomly
sample from the memory. I might get E1
or I might get E2. Then I experience E3
and I put it in the memory and I might
get one of the three. You know, this is
the vanilla experience replay. In
practice, there is more methods like
prioritize sweeping which might tell you
which experience you want to weigh.
Maybe some experiences had a higher
gradient, so you want to prioritize them
more often. You know, things like that.
So, all in all, this is what our
training looks like with experience
replay. We experience um E1, we train on
E1. Then we the next training iteration
is not on E2, it's on a sample from E1
and E2. Either or. The third experience
is then put in the replay memory but we
don't train on it. We train on a sample
from whatever is in the replay memory
and we repeat and that is more sample
more efficient allows more reusability
and less crossorrelation in our um
training [clears throat] batch.
Okay.
So that's called replay memory
and you can use it with mini batch
gradient descent. Note that you still
experience in the direction that the
game is played. Like we still go and
take the action as expected. We just
don't necessarily update our model
parameter based on the action that we
ended up taking. We put it in the replay
memory. We may train on it later.
[snorts]
Okay.
Um so here is how it modifies our
vanilla setup. We've added an experience
from state S to state S prime to the
replay memory. You know, like let me
walk you through it again. Within one
time step, we forward propagate our
state into the Q network. We execute the
best action given the Q values. This
gives us a reward and the next state.
The next state is pre-processed. And
then instead of training on that,
instead of training, we just add that
transition to the replay memory. And
instead we sample randomly a mini batch
of transition from the replay memory and
we train on those and we redo the same
thing again and again.
>> Yes.
replay bias towards the start of the
game [clears throat] sample from
everything. So, aren't you more likely
to trade start game
just like you would sometimes want?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, you you you would uh you would
within one episode, but you know, if you
if you play multiple chess game, uh your
replay memory would get already bigger.
So, then you would see some end game,
some middle of the game, some early
games. Yeah, good.
And in practice, it's actually useful
because uh you might imagine that in a
chess game, you know, all of us, let's
say if you're a beginner, you you see a
lot of beginning of the games. You
actually people that are beginners,
they're good at openings, but they're
bad at end games because they don't get
to play a lot of end games. Uh well,
that type of approach could be useful.
You can retrain on end games more often.
And you know the a more advanced version
of the replay memory
would also weigh the experience in the
replay memory based on how much the
gradient is going to be. So if you have
an experience that actually was super
insightful, you can weigh it higher so
that you you you prioritize grabbing it
and retraining on it essentially.
So let's say you blunder in chess, you
might actually want to receive that
blunder later so that you don't do it
again.
Um okay so these were all the different
methods. Another one that's very um
intuitive and very important is when
during the training process our um agent
gets stuck gets stuck in a local minima.
Uh here is how it would work in
practice. Uh you start in initial state
s1 and you have three states ahead of
you. If you take action a1 you go to
state two which is a terminal state. If
you take and you get a reward of zero.
If you take action A2, you get to S3
also a terminal state and you get a
reward of one. And if you get um action
A3, get to state four terminal state
with a reward of a,000. So of course to
us it's obvious that we would want to
explore the state number four. It's
pretty obvious in practice. Let's say
you update you you initialize your
network and in the first forward path
that's what you get first forward path
the network is random you get Q value
for action one.5
for action 2.4 four for action 3.3.
What does that mean? It means the agent
is saying I'm going to go to action one.
So I take action one and I see an
immediate reward of zero. Right? Because
it's a terminal state. The Bman equation
thing doesn't happen. I just have the
immediate reward which becomes my target
Y. And so I perform a gradient descent
update to say this Q value should have
been zero.
So I convert this Q value to zero.
Now second try.
This time the Q value is saying take
action two. It's the highest Q value. I
take action two. I have an immediate
reward ahead of me. That's one because
it's a terminal state. There's no second
discounted future reward term. Um so I
just take Y equals 1. I perform my
gradient descent updates and this
converts to one. And then third time the
agent is still saying go to A2. Go to
the take action A2 reward of one. Good.
That's what you predicted. Nothing to
do. Just keep going. We're done with
training. We're stuck. We never visit
the state we actually wanted to visit.
Okay. So that that that wouldn't work
for us. We will never visit that state
using our current algorithm. Does that
make sense why we wouldn't ever visit
that state?
In practice, this is a big issue. The
analogy of this uh concept of
exploration versus exploitation is when
every day you take your bike and you
cross um campus, you have a favorite
route. And turns out that the more you
take that route, the better you get
every time. Like you get a little
faster. Maybe your turn is faster or
something or you can predict how many
people are going to be at that
roundabout and you know how to take it
in the wide way so you go faster. We've
all done that. Um that's exploitation.
You exploit what you already know and
you get better at it. But maybe there's
another route that you're not thinking
of that's pretty instead of going north
from campus, you go south and maybe it
might be better. You will never see
because you don't have the courage or
the patience to do it. That's the
difference between exploration and
exploitation.
In practice, a good model would be able
to handle both to exploit when 22 to
exploit to explore when it needs to
explore. The way we do it in practice in
our pseudo code is to inject some
randomness. So for example, when we are
looping over time step with probability
epsilon let's say 5% take a random
action. So from time to time on average
one time every 20 times you take a
random action it will allow you to visit
maybe a new path. The analogy in chess
is you know you might use a creative
move from time to time that might be
worse today but might allow you to learn
something and to get better over time.
>> Yeah. Um in that uh the example we just
covered, couldn't we resolve that by
just setting the initial um Q values to
infinity?
>> Setting the the Couldn't we resolve this
problem by setting the initial values
from into infinity? Well, the problem if
you set the initial values to infinity.
So you would say instead of randomly
initializing your network, you
initialize it in a way that the outputs
are equal to infinity.
>> Yeah. so that we wouldn't get the issue
of where like the Q value of action
three state one is
>> well in practice if the three Q values
are infinity then you can't make a
decision on the spot so you're saying
just pick one randomly
because if the three are infinity you
you can't decide which one to take right
and also if in if it's infinity and the
reward is one I mean if it's a really
large number and the reward is one your
gradient is going to be massive right so
it's going uh I guess the loss function
is going to be massive and um I don't
know I imagine it would be really hard
to train it but in practice you start
with the random initialization because
in this might be one example but you
know if in the game of chess um actually
the the reward is one at the end and
zero all the time or maybe the reward is
a thousand at the end and when you lose
your rook it's uh it's a negative
reward. You can't predict what the
reward structure is going to be. We want
an agent that is able to adapt to it and
um it's better to find a method that can
scale to different environments
essentially. [snorts] Um
okay so this was um epsilon greedy
action which is adding some randomness
with probability epsilon take a random
action. Okay, so adding all our
techniques because we get good at
training reinforcement learning
algorithms. This is what we have. We
initialize our Q network parameters. We
have a random network. We initialize our
replay memory D. And then we loop over
episodes. We start from an initial
state. We create a boolean that allows
us to detect terminal states with
probability epsilon. We're going to take
a random action. Otherwise, we're going
to follow what we know, which is forward
propagate the state in the Q network.
take the action that has the highest Q
value that allows you to observe a
reward and the next state take that next
state forward propagate it again
instead and then and then instead of um
uh oh no sorry observe that next state
add it to the replay memory sample from
the replay memory and then train on that
sample and in the process you will need
to do another forward path because you
need to estimate your target by using
the immediate reward plus the belman
equation plus the discounted future
reward.
Okay, are you experts at Q-learning?
Okay, good. Sounds good. And here is
where we get at the end. You can claim
proudly you have trained an atari. It's
not that complicated as you can see
other than the Bellman equation piece.
Turns out the agent has discovered that
it can send the ball on the back and
it's actually much easier to finish the
game like that which is quite
interesting. You know, a good player
would know that you can dig a tunnel and
you can finish the game without too much
issues. Yeah.
>> How do you
actually
>> How do you quantify when uh when the
game has ended?
>> How would the model come after the
train?
>> Yeah. Well, uh, first you would you
would you would start seeing um the
model get to good rewards as it play
like it manages to get really good
rewards while earlier it might not, you
know, and so that's probably your best
guess for how good the model is. In
practice, if you're AlphaGo, you can
also test it against the best humans in
the world and you can observe that
they're losing against the model.
I'm saying you have like a bunch of
different [clears throat] chest engines
and some of them are way way better than
others. They have different
maybe they're both based on
reinforcement learning and at the end
they maximize both of their rewards.
>> Yeah.
>> So how do you know which model is
actually doing better? [clears throat]
>> You can get them to play together. So
you have no idea if you do that one.
>> No, you you could you could actually
monitor the loss function and look at is
the Bellman equation respected. If the
Bellman equation is respected, then your
model is really really good. And then we
we're going to see an example of
competitive selfplay where you get the
model to play against other models and
then over time as you watch them play
for thousands and thousands of time, you
can tell which model is ahead of another
one. You can then sort of copy paste the
best model into the other models and
then make them play again for many
times. And because you have the epsilon
greedy approach, one of the model is
naturally going to get better than the
others because of the randomness that
you add.
Um, okay, let's look at a few examples
and then we'll spend 20 minutes on the
RLHF. Um, here are other examples. This
is Pong uh which is one v one sequest
which is an underwater game. And then
the one that maybe more of you know
Space Invaders very popular game as
well. [sighs]
So the impressive thing that they showed
is that you can um actually solve many
games with the exact same algorithm,
no tweaks, which is quite impressive.
>> [snorts]
>> Let's go a little further and talk about
um advanced topics. Um here is a game
called Montezuma Revenge. Um this game
is particular because you're controlling
a little character right here. And this
character is trying to go and grab,
let's say, this key right here, and it
has some obstacles or some enemies that
it needs to take care of.
What what do you think is going to be an
issue if we apply what we just learned
to this game?
What makes this game especially hard in
comparison to let's say chess or go?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah, the reward is very delayed. Like
if you start with a random network, what
are the chances that the network is
going to figure out that to get to the
key, it actually should go in the
opposite direction. It should go in the
opposite direction. It could jump down
here. It should catch the rope. The rope
will probably allow the character to go
to the ladder. It goes down the ladder.
It has to go jump up this enemy. My
guess is it's in an enemy. I'm not sure,
but I think it's an enemy because of the
color. And I know that in gaming if it
was green it might not have been an
enemy but if it's gray or red it might
be an enemy. And then go up the ladder
and grab the key. The chance is very low
that the agent is going to make that
successive good decisions to get there.
You're right. Why is it use why is it
easier for a human to actually solve
that game?
>> Intuition.
>> Intuition. Prior knowledge. So, for
example, when you look at this game,
even if you have never played it, my
guess is you would know you can go down
the ladder because you know what a
ladder is. Or you can see this little
rope and you're like, I'm going to catch
the rope. I'm going to jump and go to
the other side. And you look at this
little monster and you're like, I better
not touch this monster. Or if anything,
I will jump on top of it. Cuz you've
played Mario, let's say. So, all of this
is human intuition. uh sometimes you
would call as a baby survival instinct
like you throw the baby in the water and
suddenly it flips and it can um it can
uh swim. Those are things that are to a
certain extent encoded in our DNA but at
the very least encoded in our experience
of doing other things that have nothing
to do with this game. And so the the
problem here is called imitation
learning. Is is there a better way to
start our network than a random
initialization that allows the network
to for example guess that this is a
ladder and turns out that if the network
knows that it will be more likely to get
to the reward first and then learn from
that reward and then get better over
time.
The other part that can also use human
knowledge which is what we're going to
see together is reinforcement learning
from human feedback where you have an
analogy here which is you can train a
language model and it might be
completely misaligned with what actually
humans care about. How does
reinforcement learning help in those
situations? That's going to be the next
topic in the last part of the lecture.
[snorts] Okay, let me show you a few
other results um quickly. Today we
talked about DQ and deep Q learning. In
practice there's a lot more
reinforcement learning algorithm but you
got the gist of it. You got the concept
of making good sequences of decision
epsilon greedy exploration exploitation
um terminal state starting state all of
that you you got the one the one
algorithm that is very popular right now
is called PO proximal policy
optimization. There is one that is even
more popular right now that's actually
from a year ago at Stanford called DPO
that we won't study in the class. One of
the things to know about PO just just to
go over it really quickly and and I I
pasted two important papers from
Schulman a few years back trust TRPO and
PO um is that it is not a value based
algorithm. So in Q-learning you learn
the Q values and then you define your
policy as the arg max of the Q values.
In PO, you learn the policy directly,
which is a more probabilistic method.
[snorts] Um, it also works well with
continuous spaces. If you look at the
Q-learning, we learned one output for
one action. If you actually have um a
game that has continuous action like
autonomous driving where it's not like
just turn the wheel to the right or to
the left, it's like what degree you turn
it, it's continuous. then Q the QN would
not work well or you would have to
granularize the number of action a
little bit to the right a little bit
more a little more which would not be
really useful instead you would use PO
>> yeah so question is how do you define a
reward in DQN um different reward
structure will lead to different uh
types of you know agent strategies. Uh
but you're right for the game of go you
could actually define the reward as one
if you win and zero if you don't win.
That's it. You know every move will be
zero until the last move is a win. In
chess you might actually do intermediate
reward because you want to tell the you
want to tell the agent that it's good to
kill the opponent's pieces to get rid of
them. You could also do end to end and
say I don't give any intermediate
reward. I just give a final reward which
might be more complicated to train on
but it might actually lead to a more
optimal strategy because in fact you
could actually win without taking any
piece from your opponent. So
other [snorts] things about PO is um you
know it's more probabilistic. It has a
concept of an expected advantage which
at every steps instead of telling you
how good that action is, it would tell
you how much better it is than random
than than the current state like how
much better would it be to do certain
thing versus what you would have done
otherwise. I'm not going to go into the
details. It's all in the paper. But
those are things that are important.
Here's a few examples of PO. So this
example on the left is from open AI a
few years back where you can see it's a
continuous space where uh the agent is
being um bullied a little bit but um
it's trying to grab the rewards but it's
also subject to external forces that are
sort of throwing balls at it. It's a
little bit mean, but
um you can imagine that this is a
continuous space, meaning you're
controlling the nodes, you're
controlling the joints of the agent, and
you're controlling the forces, the
angles, and so it's a that's why PO
would be better in that case.
Super. Here's a competitive selfplay,
which I really like
where you have agent play with each
other. And this is the sumo game. Push
the opponent outside the ring and you
get a reward.
So actually it's interesting because
you're seeing some emergent behavior
which is they attack each other's feet
or they lower their center of gravity to
be more stable for example. Yeah.
[laughter]
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's versions sometimes
different initializations for example.
>> So no but good question. So often time
what open would do back you know back in
that time is they would create copies of
the same model they would initialize
them differently and they would let them
learn and turns out one of the model
will get better than the others and then
they will copy again that model to the
rest and do the same thing again and
again pretty much.
Oh yeah it's kind of funny isn't it?
That's a good catch.
Yeah,
that's a good goal. [laughter]
Could watch that for hours. Okay,
they're a little awkward, you have to
say, but but it it works. Okay, so this,
you know, I let you watch the video,
it's going to be shared, but um here's
another set of games that are even more
complicated that I mentioned early on.
Open AAI 5 which you can think of an
equivalent of League of Legend Dota
where you have um 5v5 game so you have
to collaborate etc which makes it adds
like literally one additional um degree
of complexity. Uh and Starcraft uh Alpha
Star from Deep Mind is an example of
where the observation is not the entire
state you have fog and so that adds
another layer of complexity. not going
to see that together today. Um,
I would encourage you to look at the
AlphaGo documentary on Netflix if you
haven't. Who has seen it already?
Nobody. Okay. Well, um, you can now
watch it with a different eye,
understanding reinforcement learning.
And at some point in the in the
documentary, you will see that um Alph
Go makes a very odd move, a very
creative move. And people are like, I
don't understand that move. Even the top
researchers or the best players would
say in the video, they don't understand
that move. It turns out that that move
is very unintuitive for humans because
as humans, we are trained to maximize
our chances of winning. Like literally,
if I can eat all your pieces in chess, I
will eat all your pieces. And if I can
surround your stones in go as much as I
can, I will do it. The agent is just
programmed to win. So that move actually
look counterintuitive because the agent
doesn't care about winning by one or
winning by a, you know, 20 stones. It
just cares about winning. And that move
specifically put the agent in a good
place to win by a small margin. Yeah. So
that's an example of an insight that you
will learn. you you understand from this
class and you will see in the in the
documentary.
Okay, I think we have 10 minutes. I'm
I'm just going to introduce uh
reinforcement learning from human
feedback because it's a more um modern
topic that um is very trendy right now.
It's important to know and so let's look
at it together. We're going to start by
recapping how language models are
trained in a nutshell and then we'll see
what self what supervised fine-tuning
looks like. We'll talk about how do we
train a critique model, a reward model
and then finally what RLHF looks like
and why is it so trending in the news.
So [snorts]
um our training objective for language
models is next token prediction, right?
We've already talked about it in a
former lecture. The idea is that I will
get some inputs. I'm reading Wikipedia,
let's say, or some sort of a text online
and I read a sentence and I predict the
last token and I do that again and
again. So for example, deep learning and
then deep learning
is deep learning is
so deep learning is so cool
and that's it. Um, so you get the idea,
right? you always predict the next token
and then over time it forces the model
to um explicit u um emerging behaviors
and it understands the connections
between those concepts and it's really
good at generating text. We compute a
loss function. You're actually going to
study this loss function in uh C 5. So
I'm not going to talk about it right
now, but you perform, you know, a
gradient descent loop. And this is how
you get your first pre-trained language
model. Get a pre-trained language model.
You can call it on a text or a prompt
and it will continually generate and you
call it again and again and again and it
generate generate generates. Everybody's
comfortable with that, right? Okay. So,
uh that's how we trained a language
model. But there is a couple of
problems. The first problem is that
online data does not reflect
helpfulness.
So to give you a concrete example um
what you might find in the training set
is something like deep learning is so
cool when actually what you might find
in practice is people asking what is
deep learning.
So the data is not really reflective of
you want an agent to be helpful and
that's a problem because the model was
trained to continue text rather than
answer questions
and in practice you would see it's a big
problem. Another problem is the model
has no concept of good, polite, or
helpful yet. And to give you a concrete
example, you might actually ask a
pre-trained language model, my laptop
won't turn on. What should I do? And
then the model responds because it has
Reddit on Reddit or on Wikipedia is
laptops sometimes don't turn on because
of power issues. Um, which is not what
you ask. You ask what should I do? And
in fact, a better answer would have been
check your charger if is properly
[clears throat] connected or the outlet
works. If that's fine, try holding the
power button for 10 seconds. If it still
doesn't start, the battery or motorboard
may blah blah blah blah. That's a better
answer. That's what you want an a
language model to do nowadays. Um, and
the model um can give you factual text
because that's what it's been trained
on, but it's it doesn't understand being
helpful or um having an answer that
looks like a humanlike answer.
So our solution to it will start with
using supervised fine-tuning um which is
going to be learning from human written
demonstrations of helpful behavior and
then we get to even further and use RHF
which will optimize not only for human
written sentences or paragraphs but for
preferences and the word preference is
the keyword. Let's talk about how we can
improve our pre-trained model with
supervised finetuning.
I'll take um that we want to align
models with human written responses
and the step one that we're going to
lose is to build a data set. Let's build
a data set of human prompt response
pairs. So what actually open is going to
do I'll explain it in a second is it
might collect some of the prompts that
we all use and then ask humans to
respond to those prompts and put that in
a data set. It might al also ask
separately experts to write really good
prompts and then answer those prompts.
It's a fully human-made data set. And
then we use that data set to fine-tune
our pre-trained model. And by now you've
learned fine-tuning in the online video.
So you know what I'm talking about using
supervised learning. So what it looks
like is I take my pre-trained model that
I just told you how we train and then I
give it a prompt explain deep learning
to a beginner and I also will
concatenate to it a response a good
response written by a human. Deep
learning is a type of machine learning
that uses neural
and then I expect the model to come up
with the word networks.
So it's literally do whatever we did to
train the pre-trained model but we do it
on human written front response pairs
and if you do that many times and you
use the you know the same loss function
how far the model's response is from a
human response um you do that many times
and you will get SFT supervised
fine-tuning
um but it has some shortcomings
One of the shortcomings is it is data
that is extremely costly to collect. In
fact, I believe in the first version of
that instruct GPT there was only 13,000
prompt response pairs and turns out it
did really well despite that.
Um the second aspect is it's unlikely to
generalize well because you're again
you're not doing reinforcement learning
here. You're doing supervised learning
and so you're just showing a set of
examples 13,000 examples that you want
to learn but it's what tells you that it
will generalize to an unseen prompt that
will come up from your user base. And so
this approach SFT really teaches the
model to imitate good behavior from
humans. And that's the key. It's it's
imitation. It is not preference
optimization.
To do preference optimization,
that's where we're going to train a
reward model and we're going to do
proper RHF. So let me talk to you about
the RM reward model and then I'll tell
you about RHF in a nutshell.
The problem of um RHF is to align not
with human responses but with human
preferences.
So what what's going to happen is we're
going to train a separate model to
predict which responses human prefer and
we're going to call that model the
reward model. It's a separate model from
whatever we've trained before. The model
um is going to use data from labelers.
So you're going to show labelers two or
more responses to the same prompt
and those responses will be sampled from
the SFT. So your best model right now is
the SFT. You will sample three or four
responses and you know how we sample
right you you can tweak the temperature.
You can select not only the top priority
word, the top the softmax layers number
one word, but you can sometimes sample
differently and you will get a variety
of answers. And then you will ask a
human labeler to say answer B is better
than answer C and answer C is better
than answer A and answer A is sort of
equal to answer D. Let's say
um
they will be asked which response they
prefer and it can get more complicated.
It doesn't have to be just a simple
ranking. You you have multiple liker
scale methods and so on. But the the
point is that you will collect those
pair-wise comparison that we call
preference data and you will use it to
train a reward model which is
initialized from your SFT. So your SFT
is here. It's your best model to date
and you're going to modify the last
layer. So the softmax layer at the end
of a language model that will tell you
this is the token we should output or
this is the word we should write. Um
instead of that you'll get rid of that
layer. You'll put a scalar value as
output. You'll put a linear layer with a
scalar value that will represent the
reward head. It will predict the the
reward you know uh which is a proxy for
the preference of the human. The way
you'll train that reward model is you'll
give it um a batch of two um you know
you give it a prompt X with a response A
and the preference of the user and
you'll give it the same prompt with a
response B from the SFT with the
preference of the user. So here the user
is saying response A is better than
response B. And so if you actually were
sending that in this model, you will get
a predicted reward for the preferred
answer and a predicted reward for the
this preferred answer
that allows you to uh train using a loss
function that I'm not going to cover
given our our time sensitivity. The loss
function will encourage the model to
assign higher rewards to preferred
responses. So you're trying to
dissociate the higher reward better
preference from the lower reward for
lower preference. And it turns out that
if you do that many times, you will have
a reward model that given a prompt and a
response will be approximating human
preference. So you've just trained a
critique that represents your humans.
It's a proxy for what humans prefer.
It's [clears throat] been trained on a
lot of human preferences.
The reason it's better to use a model
than actual humans is because we can use
it widely on all sorts of inputs and it
can scale from a data standpoint.
Also note that this method is better
than SFT because it's way easier to ask
humans what's your preference between
those two things and to ask them to come
up with answers to prompts. Takes way
less time. And if you've used SH GPT,
you've probably been asked before to to
to tell them which response you prefer.
Yeah. So once trained the reward model
represses the human as the evaluator
during reinforcement learning with from
human feedback and reinforcement
learning from human feedback is very
comfortable for you. Now I will I will
show you what it looks like given the
Q-learning algorithm we learned. But
essentially we we have first talked the
model what good behavior looks like with
SFT and then we built a reward model
that can tell us how good an answer is
according to human preferences and the
RHF approach is where we will let this
model practice get scored by the reward
model or the critic and update itself to
produce higher scoring answers. So more
preferred answers and it's the same as
the games we've seen together but some
things differ. So I just pasted here the
exact setup that we've learned together
um for reinforcement learning. The
differences are the following. You know
our objective is still to maximize
expected reward that is produced um by
the reward model aligned with human
preferences.
The agent is the language model being
fine-tuned.
The environment is the space of possible
prompts and continuations.
It's any any text that you can
encounter. The state is the specific
prompt plus the tokens that were
generated so far. The next state is one
more token added and the action is the
next token that is chosen by the agent
or the model.
which is of course determined by the
policy
[laughter] and then the reward is
estimated by the reward model that we
trained to represent human preferences.
Okay,
in this case one episode is one full
prompt. So imagine that you get a prompt
and you start generating and you go
through this reinforcement learning loop
and you observe the rewards and then you
try to maximize the future rewards and
then at the end of training you end up
with having your pre-trained model turn
into an SFT and your SFT turn into a way
better model using RHF.
[clears throat]
Okay, so a few things to note to end on
this. The model does not get a reward at
every single token. It gets a reward at
the end of a sequence when the
completion is finished because reward
model was uh was asked to rate prompts
and responses together. So you need to
finish the generation in order to see
what's the reward. And so again going
back to making good sequences of
decision that's exactly it. You want the
model to make enough good sequences of
decision so that the response is
preferred by the critique which
represents a proxy to the human
preferences.
So all intermediary rewards are
typically zero and that makes it a very
sparse reward episodic tasks just like a
game of chess where you only get a
reward when you finish assuming you're
not defining intermediary reward. So you
only know if you did well at the end and
you have to then use that information to
update your network and get a better
proxy for it. Super. There's a very nice
video. We're not going to play it for
the sake of time, but I will send it
online. Uh it's from 4 days ago. It's uh
you know
former Stanford
students Andre Karpati who is very
thoughtful and articulate and was
explaining 4 days ago why reinforcement
learning can be terrible at times and
that human minds work way more
efficiently. And so I would encourage
you to watch this 4-minute video because
he's very clearly outlining why
reinforcement learning is still not
great even if it's the best thing we can
use in many ways.